[Music]
Hey, hey,
hey, hey.
[Music]
Well, good morning everyone and welcome
to the Fiber Broadband Association's
Five for Breakfast. We're now in our
32nd episode of 2024. Before I kick off,
I'd like to thank Wes Westco and Gha the
platinum sponsors of five for breakfast.
Yeah, I'm currently here in Buenus Aries
for our third Latin America Fiber
Connect event of 2025. You know, the
event has been amazing at maximum
capacity and the sessions have been just
incredible. you know, back in the US,
um, Congress is in recess and will be
back on September 2nd to address the
remaining appropriations bill before
October 1 to avert a potential
government shutdown. You know, yesterday
at Mountain Connect in Denver, NTI Chief
of Staff Brooke Dalon stated that 46
states have run and completed their
benefit of the bargain round. The final
bead proposals are due to NTIA on
September 4th. You know, when I get back
from South America, we'll be heading up
to Canada for our next North American
Fiber Connect workshop in Toronto on
Tuesday, August 19th. After Toronto,
we'll be in Spokane in September,
Scottsdale in October, Kansas City in
November, and then we'll end the year in
Palm Springs at our premier member
meeting in December 8th and 9th. Today
on Fire for Breakfast, our guest is
Andrew Butcher, the president of the
Maine Connectivity Authority to discuss
driving connections, local lessons from
the road to broadband expansion. Before
I formally today's guest, I'd like to
introduce David Norris from team walk us
through some housekeeping items.
>> Thank you very much, Gary, and thank you
to everybody for joining us today. We
appreciate it. And uh before I go into
the housekeeping items, we'd like to
once again thank our platinum sponsors
of Fiber for Breakfast, Westco and Gaia.
Now, as participants, you are in listen
only mode today. To ask a question,
please type it into the question box
located within the control panel on the
side of your screen, and we will host a
Q&A session with our panelists today uh
after the presentation. This is being
recorded, will be available on FDA's
website within 24 to 48 hours, and you
can find that recording in the events
tab under the fiber for breakfast
dropown option. Finally, at the
conclusion of today's presentation,
you'll be prompted to complete a brief
feedback survey. If you could take a
moment to do so, we appreciate the
input. And with that, I will hand things
back over to Gary to get us started.
Gary.
>> Thanks, Dave, and good morning. I'm Gary
Bolton, the president CEO of the Fiber
Broadband Association. You know, last
week on Fiber Breakfast, our guest was
Jim Martin, the CEO of Cityet, discussed
bridging the divide in the mountain
state, Cynet's role in rural broadband
expansion. You know, Jim is a really
interesting guy and as he's um described
himself as being self-employed his
entire career as he's built cityet into
one of the top ISPs in West Virginia.
You know, West Virginia is ground zero
for, you know, how the bead program is
going to work out. you know, um, Kelly
Workman, the state broadband director,
had delivered to NTIA a final proposal
that had a 100% fiber and it was $200
million below budget uh before going
back to the benefit of the bargain
round. So, we'll see what happens. But
Jim discussed uh public private
partnerships and the models that have
worked and then what's required to get
everyone in West Virginia um connected
with fiber. So if you missed last week's
session, you can go to the FBA website
and watch the replay. Today on Fire for
Breakfast, our guest is Andrew Butcher,
the president of the Maine Connectivity
Authority, discuss driving connections,
local lessons from the road to broadband
expansion. So Andrew has served as the
inaugural president of the Maine
Connectivity Authority since 2021.
MCA is Maine's quasi governmental agency
charged with achieving universal access
of affordable high-speed broadband
throughout the state of Maine. By
balancing investments in projects,
places, and people, MCA is advancing
digital equity for all. As the author's
first employee, Butcher was charged with
starting up the agency and scaling
capacity to receive and employ and
administer close to half a billion
dollars in federal and state funding.
Since 2021, uh, Butcher has built a high
performant performing team, an
organization designed to deploy 12
distinct funding programs, delivering
over $250 million of activities,
resulting in over a 100 grants and
contracts utilizing a variety of
strategies and technologies effective in
uh bridging Maine's digital divide. Uh
Andrew has over 15 years of experience
in community and economic development,
social entrepreneurship, and connecting
connected infrastructure. Prior to his
role at MCA, he founded and ran an
internationally recognized nonprofit,
served as the director of the Maine
Broadband Coalition, and helped advance
numerous innovations and resilience
initiatives in Maine. He lives in
Portland with his family and he's known
to his children for repairing the family
waffle maker and listened to reae while
making said waffles. Well, I'm almost
suddenly getting hungry for some
waffles, Andrew. But, um, welcome
Andrew. And for audience, please type in
your questions to go. And with that, uh,
we will get things started. I'll turn
things over to Andrew.
>> Wonderful. Thanks so much, Gary. Uh
pleasure to be here and I'm glad to be
able to bring a little breakfast
reference to our session this morning.
Um also Gary, thanks so much to you and
your team for uh hosting me at Fiber
Connect this year in Nashville. It was a
pleasure to join. Um such a incredible
event and gathering and just a
tremendous opportunity to learn,
commiserate, connect with new people. Um
so it's a pleasure for us to be able to
attend. Uh I also want to extend a a
thanks. I've got a couple team members
listening now and likely in the future.
But um just to uh the connectivity
authority team, our network of partners
and vendors uh who are as we speak
furiously working on uh execution of our
B uh final proposal um amidst a number
of other reporting requirements and
projects and initiatives, our team is
hard at work right now allowing for me
to have the time and space to do this.
So, I just appreciate you all so much.
Um, so, uh, Gary, I think one of the
things that brings me to chatting with
you all, and I'm going to share screen
here, um, and I'm going to walk through
a storyboard
of, uh, a recent trip that, uh, I took
in my 1984 Westfailia VW van. Um, aptly
named Buttercup. For those that are
viewing the screen, it's a a buttery
colored old van. Um, and uh, in June, I
drove 900 miles around the state to
visit uh, a handful of our partners and
projects. Um, and to, if nothing else,
test a hypothesis that I've been kind of
uh, scratching at a little bit. You
know, I spend all day every day uh, with
the Maine Connectivity Authority. as you
introduced means quasi governmental
agency responsible for expanding our
digital infrastructure so that everyone
benefits. Um I spend all day every day
uh trying to make sure people get
online. Um and I spend all night every
night trying to make sure that my
children are not online. Um, and um,
I've had a little bit of a fear and a
hypothesis that the more connected we
are digitally, the um, more isolated we
are from a humanity standpoint. Uh, I
know I'm not the only one who spends
time thinking about this, but I really
wanted to um, given the last four years
of progress, take a minute and have as
many conversations as possible and and
try to test that hypothesis.
Um, and part of the reason we we opted
to take this approach with the our
driving connections tour was that, you
know, this van Buttercup has this
uncanny ability to connect with people.
Um, and truly, whether it's an old
grizzly Harley-Davidson rider or a a
hippie-dippy fish uh fish uh festival go
um this van makes people smile. Um,
everywhere I go, people come to me um
and have a story or I literally was
stopped in a parking lot and someone
told me their life dream about living in
one of these vans. Um, and so when we're
talking about how to facilitate more of
a human-touman connection, uh, Buttercup
has been a pretty wonderful bridge
builder. So, um, uh, it was a great
opportunity to be able to set out and to
visit a handful of projects around the
state. And so, what I want to do is I'm
just going to walk through a little bit
of the tour with a couple key
stories and perspectives. And this story
map is going to be shared with folks
online. Please take a look at it. And
essentially our starting point here is
just an overview of the tour. What's
important with this is it sort of
reflects a couple key things. First of
all, we've got my route mapped out, but
we also see um a handful of well, we see
a significant amount of territory with
different coloration of areas. and those
represent a number of our infrastructure
projects that we've helped facilitate
with partnerships over the last couple
years. It highlights a red and blue
dotted line that looks vaguely like a
moose head um that reflects the main
open optical statewide enabling network
or moosenet. our new middle mile
initiative that we are underway building
right now uh through a competitive grant
with NTIA in partnership with the main
department of transportation and the
University of Maine system. And so this
map showcases one projects that have
been funded the route I've taken musenet
but it also showcases at a high level
that we live in a pretty big state and
for folks that are not really familiar
with Maine we have a population of about
1.4 4 million people in a state that is
threequarters the size of Pennsylvania.
That means there's a there's a a lot of
space and not a lot of humans. We have
very hilly uh ragged coastlines. We have
hilly mountains. We have granite laden
soil um and a lot of trees in the pine
tree state. And so um it is important
when we think about how structure
dictates function and the the reality
that we also have the highest
concentration of rural population in the
country also with one of the oldest if
not the oldest population in the
country. So it's important as we look at
the map right the map is not the
territory but the map does help us
understand some of the dynamics that we
are working with um and how we have
approached our connectivity
comprehensive connectivity strategy over
the last couple years. So I'm going to
just highlight a there's no way I'm able
to share with you all and the time that
we have the breadth of conversations and
talking with community partnerships and
uh you know the in in western Maine we
started the trip um taking a look at how
a collection of communities and
municipalities have come together to
invest in not just a public private
partnership but a range of different
connectivity initiatives whether Whether
it's public Wi-Fi at a a solar facility,
whether it is targeted education
training at the local
uh vocational school, um whether it is
embedding and supporting digital
navigators at local recovery centers, uh
building out and deploying capital
projects funds to be able to support
community anchor institutions expanding
their use in their facility through
organizations like the Hope Association.
What I want to as a starting point
story, I'm going to spend Gary about the
next five to eight minutes as I talk
through the tour with maybe three
stories of a specific nature. And I'm
I'm sort of landing here in western
Maine with the town of Bethl and Western
Maine. We're talking Oxford County. You
see on the map here a number of
different infrastructure projects that
have been supported with uh capital
projects funds over the course of the
last couple years. And you know, it's
important as we met with the town
officials in Bethl who, you know, this
is one of those things that we don't
really think about, but Bethl was
probably tip of the spear in
facilitating a multi- town public
private partnership on the back of a
regional effort to educate communities
around how to advance broadband
development. Over the last probably
seven years, that's been happening.
Bethl, uh, small town in western Maine,
uh, had to move out of their town office
due to a mole problem. They moved to the
airport. At the airport, they realized
they had six different town facilities
in a small town and were paying three
different internet service providers. In
an effort to consolidate their internet
costs, they reached out to neighboring
communities. Those neighboring
communities ultimately ended up
partnering together to be able to
facilitate a multi-town
initiative that allowed for aggregated
demand to be able to approach the local
internet service providers and
facilitate a very competitive process to
be able to get best possible response.
um ultimately bringing together the
regional internet service provider who
brought dollar for-dollar match to a
regional um funding initiative that MCA
was happy to support in support of what
was that multi-town educational
initiative.
So, you know, I think it's it is models
like this that are so key to success in
Maine. Um, you know, when you have uh a
highly rural population, it is a
reflection of how engaged and informed
citizens really do have the ability to
come together and drive demand. And I
think that is one of the most important
lessons that was refined and sort of put
in perspective in Western Maine. You
know, you've got key folks that then
complement that effort from a digital
navigation standpoint. So, even in the
town of Bethl's library, you know, the
image we're looking at here, this is Jim
Wittmann, and we're sitting in the
Whitman Library that his
greatgrandfather founded in Oxford
County. And Jim is not only the go-to
technical expert, he's also the local
school bus driver. So this is a human
that is literally a just embodiment of
connection and is representing this
critical investment of all right once
we've got infrastructure in place we
also need to be able to help people
access and use and so you know it's just
a tremendous opportunity to hear from
stories from the field and you know the
gentleman that he's speaking to is the
town administrator in the town of Bethl
and so you look at these small towns
older people and not just the investment
in the infrastructure but the investment
in access to education and resources to
be able to utilize and so this is a
small example and it's as I said uh over
the course of five days traversing the
state as I scroll through the story map
here um you see that in central Maine
you know I've got buttercup with our
commissioner of economic development
Mike Deay you see here now a gathering
ing of 40 different organizations rep
throughout the state that we're
convening in a digital equity workshop.
Um, and you know, it's just helpful to
put in perspective the broad array of an
ecosystem that exists that is not just
helping advance the infrastructure
deployment, but truly helping
communities prepare for a future of
increased connectivity as we make our
way to northern Maine. And for those of
you that have been to Arusta County, you
know that uh or you may not know, but
Arista County is Maine's northernmost
county. Uh it is the size of Rhode
Island, New Hampshire, and Connecticut
combined with a population of about
40,000.
So it is highly rural, highly
agricultural. Um and as you can imagine,
connectivity is a real challenge. And so
here, you know, another great example of
how multi-organizational collaboration
is so important is meeting with the town
the the county administrator standing
next to me on the far left, Ryan
Pelleter. But also I want to highlight
uh the this woman Crystal Tilly who as a
digital navigator traverses the entire
county likely knows everybody their
computer passwords and their phone pins
to be able to provide technical
assistance through a series of digital
navigation courses offered throughout
the county in partnership with libraries
and other organizations. She's able to
do that because she's coordinating
directly with a regional partner who is
responsible for helping support
communities not just in their broadband
planning but in their assessment of
technical needs at a community level.
And so it's these people and these
characters that are so critical to the
success of our ability to deploy funding
and address our connectivity needs of
which happy to talk more about Gary, but
as you know I think it is really useful
to have a perspective of some of the
stories um and some of the key
individuals. And so, you know, as I made
my way through the state
again, here we have Fred Corey, who
essentially is the catchall IT
specialist for the Mcmack Nation, uh,
with its primary tribal lands in Austic
County. Um, we have several tri we have
four separate tribes and bands in Maine.
And as we think about trial tribal
connectivity and the unique challenges
that tribal lands and tribal residents
encounter having key partners who are
thinking about not just current needs
but the future needs of connectivity.
You know, Fred is a person who is
thinking about how can we build in
remote health care solutions through
technology to be able to address a
disperate network of tribal homes and
residents throughout the state and use
that in such a way to aggregate data to
inform the best level of procurement of
services for tribal residents. And so
people like Fred are kind of these
unsung heroes that are doing the work of
how to fuse infrastructure development
and investments in digital
opportunities.
Gary, I'm making my way from Arusa
County into Washington County, which you
know, uh, through Danforth. And this is
the Sunrise State. Uh, and in the
Sunrise State, we've got Sunrise County
in Washington County. It is uh our
oldest county and it is one of our
poorest counties. Yet the level of
multi- town organization and regional
orientation of infrastructure
development is pretty inspiring. And so
as you can see there are a number of
significant infrastructure projects that
have been invested.
This story map provides a link to those
projects and those partners. But I just
want to at least round out this portion
of storytelling with just, you know, one
small example to really illustrate the I
think the confrontation of the
hypothesis that I posed at the
beginning. Um, and I just want to
highlight the woman in the image here,
Janice. Um, a conversation in Washington
County. Um, you know, her comments were
so profound, I I wanted I I wrote them
down so that I could share in some of
our follow-up conversations.
Janice conveyed this to me in a
conversation. She said, "I spent 35
years as a school teacher. I'm a mother.
I'm a veteran. I learned to thrive in
one stream of life, and I'm now forced
into another stream through technology.
And I feel like I'm swimming in brackish
water. And I fear I would drown if not
for the shared experience to learn new
technology skills with new friends at my
local library and to be able to
understand how I can communicate to my
children and thrive in their new
and you know it's it's just amazing the
poetry that we encounter on a daily
basis.
Um, you know, Janice is a assistant town
clerk in a very small town in a very
rural county.
Um, and to have that perspective and the
proactive mention to learn new skills,
especially as the infrastructure is now
we've made great progress in May over
the last couple years.
As we mentioned in my intro, we
facilitated about 250 million in public
and private investments to drive our
connectivity or unserve from 18% to
approximately 4% um that we are looking
to serve through the process. We've
tried a number of different alternative
technologies. We emphasize the fiber to
the premise strategy first and we
recognize the balance of solving
immediate problems with the long-term
orientation and really try to address
that through comprehensive activity
which as I just finish up here you know
it's important to emphasize that that
manifests
way
the town of Bremen with a fisherman by
Bo Marsh who's been helping identified
that the town fishery and the need to be
able to connect that facility with the
fishing vessels ensuring affordable
options through the town committee. It's
a key part of how Lincoln County is able
to address a comprehensive connectivity
strategy. Here you see over two dozen
folks who came together for an evening
picnic as now Lincoln County received a
regional award in partnership with
consolidated communications
fiber to be able to be the first county
in Maine will have a comprehensive
connectivity solution in place and so
again it's a combination of libraries
digital navigators county administrators
um who are working with county jails to
be able to ensure that all residents not
just have access to technology but have
the technical assistance affordability
and access to devices that are needed to
be able to thrive.
So Gary, I'm gonna I'm happy to keep
walking through our story map here, but
I know there's a number questions to be
had discussion, but I think it's really
far too easy to um you know, our work is
all really hard, right? I'm grateful for
the time and space that fiber broadband
association provides for technical
discussion. But I also think it's really
important to keep in perspective
um the fundamental nature of
connectivity that we are looking to
address and how that manifests in really
specific ways in places like Wayne. So
thanks for the opportunity to share some
of the story here. Uh our story map is
on the website.org.
Well, Andrew, thanks for sharing your
buttercup story.
>> I love it. Broadband is about people and
that's what I really love about your
story is really connecting with people.
Uh so, you know, we have a number of
audience questions here and you know,
one was what was the most surprising
thing you learned during your trip?
um
you know in some ways uh surprising
surprising but obvious. Um, I think time
and time again I I was kind of looking
for people to to reaffirm my hypothesis,
I guess, as as one does. And in almost
every county I visited in conversation,
there was the reaffirmed emphasis that,
you know, maybe it's possible to have uh
be consumed by the internet and to lose
sight of our human connections. But the
the most prevalent response was that
this is an essential way for us to
participate, for me to be involved, for
me to be able to pursue the things that
I want.
um and the recognition that um we have a
lot of work to do to continue adapting
that to the rate of evolution of
technology. So, you know, again, it's
both surprising but obvious, but just
how
the demand and need and how strongly
people still feel about the fundamental
need for access.
Yeah, I think when I think about fiber
critical infrastructure, I think a lot
beyond internet um main you know given
your low density um and access to water
is are you seeing a lot of hyperscale or
interest in you know AI data centers in
Maine or you know we looked last week we
had a webinar where we're you know our
studies showing that we need 214 million
more miles of fiber for support AI data
centers.
Yeah. Um well, I think there's two ways
of answering that. I mean, I think first
understanding the um the energy demand
dynamic um represent the an added level
of complexity which I know you know
everyone's having to reconcile with. Um,
but I would say from our standpoint, I
think that is why the development of
Musenet as a stateowned public asset
will be so critical to addressing that
growing demand. And we are admits our
design build stage right now. And I'm
really excited to share that later in a
week or less we'll be posting an RFP to
seek um additional partnership for our
operations maintenance commercialization
engineering and so leveraging that
infrastructure to address the growing
demand whether it's through our research
and education networks whether it's
through our schools and library networks
I mean the main school and library
network is a national model for building
the foundation of digital equity and
inclusion through its bulk procurement
of services, leveraging -ate funding,
leveraging state regulatory funding
through the public utilities commission
and providing an added level of
technical assistance um and resource
development through network main and
servicing uh network of schools and
libraries. And so as we prepare for
growing an AI economy and thinking about
the role of data centers, that type of
infrastructure is going to be really key
to being in place to be able to
incentivize and support whether it's
hyperscalers or a distributed network
and ecosystem data centers.
>> You know, buttercup reminds me a I I do
a lot of whitewater kayaking and I have
friends that literally live in vans very
much like Buttercup because they are
avid whitewater kayakers. But the
problem I always have is I have to go
find a Dollar General to get online to
be have any connectivity just and I can
imagine as you threw out Maine just cell
coverage connect you know Wi-Fi any kind
of connectivity is very challenging. Is
that was that your experience or
>> Gary? Are you trying to are you trying
to bait me into a conversation about
wireless and cellular? Um because you
should. Um the I think your point is is
spot on as to the alignment of
connectivity with you know we think
about them as heritage industries in
Maine, right? Um when you look at
farming, forestry, fisheries and the
outdoor economy in Maine, the role of
having ubiquitous connectivity, not just
through fiber to the premise, but with a
comprehensive
multi-technology
set of options. We've got to be getting
out of this binary conversation. Do you
have service? Do you not? And so when we
look at whether you know it's it's the
outdoor economy and and recreational
opportunities which are now increasingly
dependent upon device access
um being able to expand our cellular
connectivity and wireless is going to be
key to success and again that is one
more way in which we are hoping to
leverage MooNet right I mean these
highly rural hilly tree covered areas
are in some ways connectivity deserts
for a reason. It is hard and costly.
If we can leverage and subsidize
Moosenet to be able to incentivize and
expand wireless cellular service, that's
essential. And then in fact actually
we're really excited to be working we
just put out an RFP earlier this year
with funding through the Northern Border
Regional Commission um to be able to
engage technical distance through Tilson
and with the local communications
partner Blaze who just put together the
outdoor economy roadmap for the state as
well. And so, um, you know, Gary, I
welcome you. I invite you to join me and
and actually main uh MCA's board chair
Tim Schneider on a kayaking whitewater
kayaking trip in April next year on the
Pasamasawasi
in uh Hancock County, which is you might
be lucky in that it's still snowing, but
there will be white water.
>> Well, I do my best white water and snow,
so um I'll definitely be there. Andrew,
Andrew, thanks again. Um, just really
appreciate you and everything your
office is doing and all the state
broadband directors. You guys just um
been doing an amazing job and uh
hopefully you guys will get some rest
after September 4th when you get your
final proposals in. I want to um thank
everybody for joining us today and look
forward to getting back together next
Wednesday. We're going to have Bill
Baker, the CEO of Nexlink, discuss fiber
and fixed wireless, a winning
combination for Nex Link. So, thanks
everyone. Um, so I'm signing off here
from Argentina and I look forward to
seeing you guys in Toronto in a couple
weeks.